<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0">
<channel>
<title><![CDATA[jasblog]]></title>
<description><![CDATA[jasblog]]></description>
<link>https://jasbrg.github.io/</link>
<lastBuildDate>Sat, 23 Jan 2021 18:58:33 -0600</lastBuildDate>
<item>
  <title><![CDATA[elfeed-org]]></title>
  <description><![CDATA[
<p>
Today I went on a little bit of a rabbit hole when configuring my RSS feeds to
please <code>elfeed-org</code>. Its configuration is simple enough, a normal org file where
the headings are feed URLs for <code>elfeed</code>, and the tags are tags and inherited
normally. Also, org-links are valid and understood. Cool!
</p>

<p>
Then I tried fitting YouTube channels into this routine, but that wasn't quite
as trivial. After some experimentation with scripts and <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bookmarklet">bookmarklets</a> the
solution I ended up using was to just find and copy the relevant URL
programmatically with a <a href="https://greasyfork.org/en/scripts/36357-youtube-copy-channel-rss-feed-url-to-clipboard">user-script</a> called through <a href="https://www.tampermonkey.net/">Tampermonkey</a>. It needed a
small modification, adding
</p>

<p>
<code>// @match        https://www.youtube.com/c/*</code>
</p>

<p>
to include the apparantly new shortened URLs, there may be more edge cases
lurking.
</p>

<p>
Then, I have a couple of entries added to <code>org-capture-templates</code> the usual way<sup><a id="fnr.1" class="footref" href="#fn.1">1</a></sup>
</p>

<div class="org-src-container">
<pre class="src src-emacs-lisp">(add-to-list
 'org-capture-templates
 '("r" "RSS Feed" entry (file+headline "~/org/feeds.org" "Inbox")
   "*** %^C"
   :prepend t :immediate-finish t))

(add-to-list
 'org-capture-templates
 '("y" "YouTube Feed" entry (file+headline "~/org/feeds.org" "YouTube")
   "**** [[%x][%^{Channel Name}]]"
   :prepend t :immediate-finish t))
</pre>
</div>

<p>
Ta-da! Done for now, I'm satisfied. Though I can foresee the obvious extension
of integrating (the lately hotly contested) <a href="https://github.com/ytdl-org/youtube-dl">youtube-dl</a>. Maybe there's already
some extension? hmm, at least not on <code>melpa</code> or <code>gnu</code>.
</p>

<p>
Envision it so: a tag is specified in some way, when the specified tag is added
to a post (through <code>elfeed</code>), it is marked for download into a specified
directory. There, I've defined a new Emacs package! :)
</p>

<p>
There is already an Emacs interface to youtube-dl, <a href="https://gitlab.com/tuedachu/ytdl">ytdl</a>. If this, we'll call it
<code>elfeed-ytdl</code>, has the two packages as a dependency the actual code to achieve
this functionality is probably under fifty lines. Perhaps!
</p>
<div id="footnotes">
<h2 class="footnotes">Footnotes: </h2>
<div id="text-footnotes">

<div class="footdef"><sup><a id="fn.1" class="footnum" href="#fnr.1">1</a></sup> <div class="footpara"><p class="footpara">
Not really as depicted. I use <a href="https://github.com/jwiegley/use-package">use-package</a> because it rocks, but it's good
practice to keep code examples relevant and if possible, executable.
</p></div></div>


</div>
</div><div class="taglist"><a href="https://jasbrg.github.io/tags.html">Tags</a>: <a href="https://jasbrg.github.io/tag-emacs.html">emacs</a> <a href="https://jasbrg.github.io/tag-musing.html">musing</a> </div>]]></description>
  <category><![CDATA[emacs]]></category>
  <category><![CDATA[musing]]></category>
  <link>https://jasbrg.github.io/20210123181413-elfeed-org.html</link>
  <pubDate>Sat, 23 Jan 2021 18:14:00 -0600</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title><![CDATA[Some Ideas]]></title>
  <description><![CDATA[
<nav id="table-of-contents">
<h2>Table of Contents</h2>
<div id="text-table-of-contents">
<ul>
<li><a href="#org77e85f7">1. org-capture-android</a></li>
<li><a href="#orgc7b7ccc">2. org-babel-wolfram-alpha</a></li>
<li><a href="#org9938523">3. spirals</a></li>
</ul>
</div>
</nav>
<p>
Some ideas I have for projects
</p>

<div id="outline-container-org77e85f7" class="outline-2">
<h2 id="org77e85f7"><span class="section-number-2">1</span> org-capture-android</h2>
<div class="outline-text-2" id="text-1">
<p>
<a href="http://www.orgzly.com/">Orgzly</a> is nice, very nice. The interface is pretty impressive for capturing as
much of Org Mode's functionality as it does, but it's more than I quite need or
want especially because I'm using a <a href="https://www.unihertz.com/jelly-2.html">Jelly 2</a>, which has a screen under 4" so
inputing great volumes of text is somewhat prohibitive. Still, I want to
interface with Org Mode from my phone despite its small size so instead of a
full featured implementation of Org Mode on Android I simply want the Org
Capture interface. The ability to program~configure~customize templates for
inputing some data, and quickly stashing it away is desirable and suitable for
the limiting form factor of a small phone. Find more information about the
<code>org-capture</code> templates <a href="org-capture-templates">here</a>.<sup><a id="fnr.1" class="footref" href="#fn.1">1</a></sup>
</p>

<p>
There appears to be some integration thought of for a mobile
protocol <a href="https://orgmode.org/manual/Org-Mobile.html">here</a> but I can't tell if this has been abandoned since. I recall a
"Mobile Org" app at some point but it has been superseded by Orgzy. 
</p>
</div>
</div>

<div id="outline-container-orgc7b7ccc" class="outline-2">
<h2 id="orgc7b7ccc"><span class="section-number-2">2</span> org-babel-wolfram-alpha</h2>
<div class="outline-text-2" id="text-2">
<p>
An Org Babel interface. Querying WolframAlpha from Org-mode is potentially
useful for a computational notebook, fluently accessing the data available in
either textual, image, or mathematica formats. The last being useful with
<code>ob-mathematica</code>. Inspired by <code>ob-rest</code> for its design.
</p>
</div>
</div>

<div id="outline-container-org9938523" class="outline-2">
<h2 id="org9938523"><span class="section-number-2">3</span> spirals</h2>
<div class="outline-text-2" id="text-3">
<p>
upwards or downwards, your choice. find the groove, your <i>wu wei</i>, the place
between being and becoming. Matthew or Pareto, either way a rose hard to name
</p>
</div>
</div>
<div id="footnotes">
<h2 class="footnotes">Footnotes: </h2>
<div id="text-footnotes">

<div class="footdef"><sup><a id="fn.1" class="footnum" href="#fnr.1">1</a></sup> <div class="footpara"><p class="footpara">
I was curious how the system would handle a <code>help:</code> link rather than the
usual <code>http:</code>, no dice, you shouldn't click this link :) in a perfect world it
would have opened in the nearest \*help\* buffer post-haste<sup><a id="fnr.2" class="footref" href="#fn.2">2</a></sup>
</p></div></div>

<div class="footdef"><sup><a id="fn.2" class="footnum" href="#fnr.2">2</a></sup> <div class="footpara"><p class="footpara">
That would be if <code>org-static-blog</code> did anything with it, but from a glance
it appears it mostly just takes the bit after the colon 
</p></div></div>


</div>
</div><div class="taglist"><a href="https://jasbrg.github.io/tags.html">Tags</a>: <a href="https://jasbrg.github.io/tag-musing.html">musing</a> <a href="https://jasbrg.github.io/tag-idea.html">idea</a> </div>]]></description>
  <category><![CDATA[musing]]></category>
  <category><![CDATA[idea]]></category>
  <link>https://jasbrg.github.io/2021-01-19-some-ideas.html</link>
  <pubDate>Tue, 19 Jan 2021 23:42:00 -0600</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title><![CDATA[Emacsen Blog Links]]></title>
  <description><![CDATA[
<p>
Here are a few Emacs blogs I like!
</p>

<div class="org-src-container">
<pre class="src src-emacs-lisp">(<span class="org-keyword">setq</span> elfeed-feeds
        '((<span class="org-string">"https://wingolog.org/feed/atom"</span> emacs blog)
          (<span class="org-string">"http://cachestocaches.com/feed"</span> emacs blog)
          (<span class="org-string">"https://jherrlin.github.io/index.xml"</span> emacs blog)
          (<span class="org-string">"https://nyxt.atlas.engineer/feed"</span> emacs lisp blog)
          (<span class="org-string">"https://www.murilopereira.com/index.xml"</span> emacs blog)
          (<span class="org-string">"https://daryl.wakatara.com/rss.xml"</span> emacs blog)
          (<span class="org-string">"https://alhassy.github.io/rss.xml"</span> emacs lisp blog)
          (<span class="org-string">"https://www.philnewton.net/blog/feed/"</span> emacs blog)
          (<span class="org-string">"https://karl-voit.at/feeds/lazyblorg-all.atom_1.0.links-only.xml"</span> emacs blog)))
</pre>
</div>
<div class="taglist"><a href="https://jasbrg.github.io/tags.html">Tags</a>: <a href="https://jasbrg.github.io/tag-emacs.html">emacs</a> <a href="https://jasbrg.github.io/tag-links.html">links</a> </div>]]></description>
  <category><![CDATA[emacs]]></category>
  <category><![CDATA[links]]></category>
  <link>https://jasbrg.github.io/2021-01-16-emacsen-blog-links.html</link>
  <pubDate>Sat, 16 Jan 2021 18:41:00 -0600</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title><![CDATA[Zathura from the Mountain]]></title>
  <description><![CDATA[
<p>
Part of my resolutions for the new year is to blog as often as possible, which
would have felt rather indulgent and narcissistic when I was older, but I'm
younger than that now. The word itself I find unattractive, the 'b' bursting
from pursed lips, the 'l' scraping past hard palate, the 'o' filling the mouth
with its round sound conjuring a glottal 'g'. It's charming though, in its
clumsiness. Originating from "web log" from when the internet was young and the
uses of the medium were less usual, more strange. Regardless of the history of
blogging it is today a useful source of technical information, as the people who
generally still have blogs are technical people. Laymen have services and
platforms with lower barrier to entry and maintenance, though this usually
entails being as the product bought and sold. Not very condusive to privacy,
security, or sanity to have quantifications of your essential nature bundled up
and sold en masse to the highest bidder aiming for your demo.
</p>

<p>
Blogging in comparison is much more wholesome so I'm not as concerned with my
potential narcissism for running one. To me at this moment keeping this blog is
a way to require something of myself which is presentable, so at least the
potential for an audience is necessary to motivate myself into keeping to that.
This comes at time when general precautionary measures are in effect so as to
avoid infection by disease, meaning contact with other people is rather scarce.
We're a social creature, humans. If you doubt this to any degree, just look to
the punitive system where solitary confinement is among the harshest punishments
that can be levied. We simply require contact, there is no two-ways about it.
The Hermit may momentarily escape the trappings of civilization in the
mountains, but the only way for his solitude to have meaning is for it to
eventually end. 
</p>
<div class="taglist"><a href="https://jasbrg.github.io/tags.html">Tags</a>: <a href="https://jasbrg.github.io/tag-musing.html">musing</a> </div>]]></description>
  <category><![CDATA[musing]]></category>
  <link>https://jasbrg.github.io/2021-01-16-keeping-web-log.html</link>
  <pubDate>Sat, 16 Jan 2021 18:06:00 -0600</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title><![CDATA[org-spreadsheet]]></title>
  <description><![CDATA[
<nav id="table-of-contents">
<h2>Table of Contents</h2>
<div id="text-table-of-contents">
<ul>
<li><a href="#org94e57ec">1. Intro</a></li>
<li><a href="#org0302d8e">2. Capture</a></li>
<li><a href="#orgffc8e7a">3. Getting deeper</a></li>
<li><a href="#org86caca4">4. Sources</a></li>
</ul>
</div>
</nav>

<div id="outline-container-org94e57ec" class="outline-2">
<h2 id="org94e57ec"><span class="section-number-2">1</span> Intro</h2>
<div class="outline-text-2" id="text-1">
<p>
This is getting pretty interesting. The spreadsheet functionality of org-tables
is more impressive than I would have guessed. For small example here's a
snapshot of a <code>diet.org</code> file I've been working on.
</p>

<pre class="example">
* Food Lookup Table
#+TBLNAME: nutrition
| name           | cal/g | fat%g | carb%g | prot%g |
|----------------+-------+-------+--------+--------|
| corn beef hash |  1.64 |    10 |     10 |      7 |
</pre>


<pre class="example">
* Food Log
#+TBLNAME: diet
| timestamp              | name           | grams | cal/g | calories |
|------------------------+----------------+-------+-------+----------|
| [2021-01-15 Fri 13:35] | corn beef hash |   198 |  1.64 |   324.72 |
#+TBLFM: $4='(org-lookup-first $2 '(remote(nutrition, @2$1..@&gt;$1)) '(remote(nutrition, @2$2..@&gt;$2)))::$5=$4*$3
</pre>


<p>
Put the point on the last line, <code>C-c C-c</code>, and ta-da!
</p>
</div>
</div>

<div id="outline-container-org0302d8e" class="outline-2">
<h2 id="org0302d8e"><span class="section-number-2">2</span> Capture</h2>
<div class="outline-text-2" id="text-2">
<p>
I'm lazy, so remembering how to record things is a bit more work than I want to
do regularly, especially since I know I don't have to with <code>org-capture</code>. I've
been having some fun with it lately as I've started using <code>org-roam</code> which has
an extension to the already featureful <code>org-capture</code>. Here I want to capture two
different things
</p>
<ol class="org-ol">
<li>Nutrition of a food</li>
<li>Amount of foot eaten</li>
</ol>
<p>
With the functionality of org tables I know I can do some computations very
easily with the information entered so that's the kind of capture I'll use.
After staring at the documentation of <code>org-capture-templates</code> for a while I
arrive at
</p>

<div class="org-src-container">
<pre class="src src-emacs-lisp">(add-to-list
 'org-capture-templates
 '((<span class="org-string">"f"</span> <span class="org-string">"Food Log"</span> table-line (file+headline <span class="org-string">"~/org/log.org"</span> <span class="org-string">"Food Log"</span>)
    <span class="org-string">"| %U | %^{name} | %^{grams} | | |"</span>
    <span class="org-builtin">:prepend</span> t <span class="org-builtin">:immediate-finish</span> t
    )
   (<span class="org-string">"F"</span> <span class="org-string">"Food Nutrients"</span> table-line (file+headline <span class="org-string">"~/org/log.org"</span> <span class="org-string">"Food Nutrients"</span>)
    <span class="org-string">"| %^{name} | %^{cal/g} | %^{fat%g} | %^{carb%g} | %^{prot%g} | "</span>
    <span class="org-builtin">:prepend</span> t <span class="org-builtin">:immediate-finish</span> t
    )))
</pre>
</div>

<p>
Reviewing, we have a list <code>org-capture-templates</code> which contains a list that
defines the capture behavior. Check out the documentation of that variable for a
full explanation. The spec of the sublists is:
</p>

<p>
<code>(key description type target template . properties)</code>
</p>

<p>
The first two are obvious, they configure the interface for this template from
the <code>org-capture</code> dispatch<sup><a id="fnr.1" class="footref" href="#fn.1">1</a></sup>. The type I use is <code>table-line</code>, which searches
for the first table at its <code>target</code>. We can configure the location within the
table with the <code>:table-line-pos</code> property, but instead I format the tables to
please the expected defaults, which (per capture-template) is a single table
with static column names. This lends itself to a quick-entry-quit cycle defined
with the <code>:immediate-finish</code> property combined with prompts for all necessary
data. I <code>:prepend</code> mostly stylistically, it's nicer to read <i>IMHO</i>.
</p>
</div>
</div>

<div id="outline-container-orgffc8e7a" class="outline-2">
<h2 id="orgffc8e7a"><span class="section-number-2">3</span> Getting deeper</h2>
<div class="outline-text-2" id="text-3">
<p>
This seems to work out well as a quick method for recording diet. Everything is
normalized around grams and cal<sup><a id="fnr.2" class="footref" href="#fn.2">2</a></sup> because that's the most straightforward
way. Nutritional science is a mystery to me, but I believe tracking
macronutrients should suffice for the level of insight I can make. Micronutrient
tracking can be done in parallel and in more of a goal based method, rather than
logging. At some point in future I could do something like the nutrition lookup
table demonstrated above, or something else&#x2026; not even sure what ought be
tracked. 
</p>

<p>
What I would like to do next is make a third table which is calculated based off
of the first two, which displays the sum of calories consumed in a day along
with the relative proportion per macronutrient. My first thought is the lookup
would be complicated by the presence of time in the diet table timestamp. So
remove that for now&#x2026;<sup><a id="fnr.3" class="footref" href="#fn.3">3</a></sup> In fact that'll be the target, just the sum of
calories in a day. The information about proportion can be done in a separate
formula, and should prove to be much more complex. Initially online I find <a href="https://emacs.stackexchange.com/questions/61391/org-mode-sum-time-from-remote-table-with-org-lookup-all">this
page</a> which is instructive.
</p>

<p>
Indeed, with a little hacking I have a working example, although it's a bit more
invloved than desired. We'll get to that later.
</p>

<p>
I add a filter one the first columnt of the diet table
</p>

<pre class="example">
#+begin_src emacs-lisp :var x=diet[1:-1]
(delete-dups (mapcar (lambda (y) (list (car y))) x))
#+end_src
</pre>


<p>
Which provides me with the deduplicated list of dates.
</p>

<pre class="example">
| [2021-01-15 Fri] |
</pre>


<p>
Name this, and sprinkle in some <code>org-table</code> magic.
</p>

<pre class="example">
#+TBLNAME: dietdaily
| timestamp        |          calories |
|------------------+-------------------|
| [2021-01-15 Fri] | 626.5400000000001 |
#+TBLFM: $2='(apply '+ (mapcar 'string-to-number (org-lookup-all $1 '(remote(diet,@2$1..@&gt;$1)) '(remote(diet,@2$5..@&gt;$5)))))
</pre>


<p>
Perfect! Well, actually this is way more involved than I want. I want to point
at a block and say "Do this!" and see it be done. Luckily these are fore-blazed
trails. Some people must use these spreadsheet feature a lot! They went and
wrote <a href="https://github.com/tbanel/orgaggregate">this</a> to generate tables from your tables. It is much better&#x2026; with just
</p>

<pre class="example">
#+begin: aggregate :table diet :cols "timestamp vsum(calories)"
#+end
</pre>


<p>
<b><i>C-c C-c</i></b>
</p>

<pre class="example">
#+begin: aggregate :table diet :cols "timestamp vsum(calories)"
| timestamp        | vsum(calories) |
|------------------+----------------|
| [2021-01-15 Fri] |         626.54 |
#+end
</pre>


<p>
Nice! No floating point fudgery. (You'll notice I added some more items to
<code>diet</code> for a sum). Representing the proportion of macronutrients will have to
wait for now, dinner's cooking and I still have to see how well this page
publishes!
</p>
</div>
</div>

<div id="outline-container-org86caca4" class="outline-2">
<h2 id="org86caca4"><span class="section-number-2">4</span> Sources</h2>
<div class="outline-text-2" id="text-4">
<ul class="org-ul">
<li><a href="https://orgmode.org/worg/org-tutorials/org-spreadsheet-intro.html">https://orgmode.org/worg/org-tutorials/org-spreadsheet-intro.html</a><sup><a id="fnr.4" class="footref" href="#fn.4">4</a></sup></li>
</ul>
</div>
</div>
<div id="footnotes">
<h2 class="footnotes">Footnotes: </h2>
<div id="text-footnotes">

<div class="footdef"><sup><a id="fn.1" class="footnum" href="#fnr.1">1</a></sup> <div class="footpara"><p class="footpara">
which I've bound to <code>C-c o c</code>, so <code>C-c o c f</code> invokes the Food Log
template
</p></div></div>

<div class="footdef"><sup><a id="fn.2" class="footnum" href="#fnr.2">2</a></sup> <div class="footpara"><p class="footpara">
America uses <code>Cal</code> where elsewhere uses <code>kcal</code>, I'll use the middle ground
<code>cal</code> to ensure incorrectness
</p></div></div>

<div class="footdef"><sup><a id="fn.3" class="footnum" href="#fnr.3">3</a></sup> <div class="footpara"><p class="footpara">
There is some interest in the time of day one eats, with respect to
intermittent fasting, but for our purposes a resolution of per-day suffices
</p></div></div>

<div class="footdef"><sup><a id="fn.4" class="footnum" href="#fnr.4">4</a></sup> <div class="footpara"><p class="footpara">
I captured this from an <code>org-roam entry</code>, so there's a few inconsistencies
(that this commit will remedy). Regarding meta-data only. Some smoothing will be
done to my exporting from <code>org-roam</code> a single keypress, but it's manually done
for this entry.
</p></div></div>


</div>
</div><div class="taglist"><a href="https://jasbrg.github.io/tags.html">Tags</a>: <a href="https://jasbrg.github.io/tag-emacs.html">emacs</a> <a href="https://jasbrg.github.io/tag-org.html">org</a> </div>]]></description>
  <category><![CDATA[emacs]]></category>
  <category><![CDATA[org]]></category>
  <link>https://jasbrg.github.io/2021-01-15-org-spreatsheet.html</link>
  <pubDate>Fri, 15 Jan 2021 18:53:00 -0600</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title><![CDATA[Hello]]></title>
  <description><![CDATA[
<p>
Coming to you from <a href="https://github.com/bastibe/org-static-blog">nearly-nine-hundred lines</a> of Emacs-lisp and a <a href="https://sandyuraz.com/styles/org.min.css">pittance</a> of
CSS. Do you really need more? <sup><a id="fnr.1" class="footref" href="#fn.1">1</a></sup> In time I'll accumulate more bits and
pieces of customization and configuration to apply, better expressing myself
through this site. As it stands now this little veneer suffices, it's never
really about what's on the cover anyway, but how effective the cover is at
appealing to those that may appreciate the content. As long as you can make out
the shapes of these letters in the order I have lain them out and we can speak
alike, you have some chance of catching my drift.
</p>

<p>
More interesting to me, than <code>family=Inconsolata</code>, is the set of pipes and gears
that thrum and turn making manifest those thoughts cannily caught, cast into
concrete from what was once ineffable as birdsong's last reflection on a sun
bleached birch tree. The fleeting formation neurons firing a whispering voice to
an inner ear which hands can transcribe, digits to digits. Ten to two (that
is one and zero) and back again, if this bird's song is sweet enough to echo off
the bark of your mind.
</p>

<p>
Emacs has long been my preferred editor, OS, and church. It's just a damn fine
piece of software.
</p>

<img src=" https://cdn.vox-cdn.com/thumbor/4p6C2WQTIBKbvVFdYk0q0_l3Wu0=/0x0:2995x3000/920x613/filters:focal(1852x1028:2330x1506):format(webp)/cdn.vox-cdn.com/uploads/chorus_image/image/54841361/twin_peaks_abc_archives.0.jpg">

<p>
There isn't much like it, comparisons to other editors are usually misguided
because it isn't anything like other editors. An old joke is Emacs is a good OS,
it just lacks a good text editor. A slightly younger joke is, that's true but we
can emulate VI now. Really it's a text programming environment
</p>
<div id="footnotes">
<h2 class="footnotes">Footnotes: </h2>
<div id="text-footnotes">

<div class="footdef"><sup><a id="fn.1" class="footnum" href="#fnr.1">1</a></sup> <div class="footpara"><p class="footpara">
Only if you need features™ like working footnotes
</p></div></div>


</div>
</div><div class="taglist"><a href="https://jasbrg.github.io/tags.html">Tags</a>: <a href="https://jasbrg.github.io/tag-hello.html">hello</a> </div>]]></description>
  <category><![CDATA[hello]]></category>
  <link>https://jasbrg.github.io/2021-01-14-hello.html</link>
  <pubDate>Thu, 14 Jan 2021 23:58:00 -0600</pubDate>
</item>
</channel>
</rss>
